[SPEAKER_00]: So, what do you mean when you talk about psychologization?
[SPEAKER_00]: How do you recognize yourself doing it, and why is it a problem?
[SPEAKER_02]: So, psychologization, the term I came up with, is basically, it means like, when you are doing, like, self-explaining to yourself, or explaining as to why and how things happen to yourself, to help you cope.
[SPEAKER_02]: You can't help doing it in the beginning.
[SPEAKER_02]: Obviously, the more successful your practice is, the less and less you'll be doing it, and eventually you wouldn't be doing any psychologization, because you're free from suffering.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, it's like the the internal mental response to being affected by dukkha.
[SPEAKER_02]: You know, like a really unrestrained person will just act with the body and punch or steal, do stuff to get what they want, so that they don't suffer.
[SPEAKER_02]: Somebody who doesn't do that, but then still affected by
[SPEAKER_02]: The world, internally, they will have to find ways of coping.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, then, it's like rationalizations, justifications, explanations.
[SPEAKER_02]: Sometimes, it's not even, like, necessarily that kind of coarse form of avoiding responsibility mentally.
[SPEAKER_02]: Well, I did it because of this.
[SPEAKER_02]: I know I couldn't, but I did it because this is what happened, and they said this, and this, and therefore, it was deserved.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's already psychological.
[SPEAKER_02]: And it's just like, it's a cover-up.
[SPEAKER_02]: Even if it was the most deserved action that you did, if you're having to explain it to yourself, it's a cover-up.
[SPEAKER_02]: means you're covering up the discomfort of it, the discomfort of responsibility of it.
[SPEAKER_02]: So that's why it's a problem, that's why it's unwholesome, because it always partakes in some degree of ignorance, of avijjā, of a cover-up.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, it could even be a subtler form as well, which would be like, you know, like, the whole practice is about understanding,
[SPEAKER_02]: But then, obviously, in order to understand the mind, you need to start to see the mind.
[SPEAKER_02]: In order to see the mind, well, you need to have been practicing the restraint and withdrawal from all the things and actions that you make that obscure the mind.
[SPEAKER_02]: And that takes time to develop.
[SPEAKER_02]: It takes faith to stick to as well, to keep doing it.
[SPEAKER_02]: So then, what people would often kind of become trapped by is that
[SPEAKER_02]: The need to understand things gets conflated with figuring things out.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, collecting the bits of information, making sense out of it in my mind, equals understanding.
[SPEAKER_02]: And that's another psychologicalization.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's another cover-up of sorts.
[SPEAKER_02]: So now, when dukkha happens, well, that's just the phassa that's affected by the, you know, sense objects.
[SPEAKER_02]: This comes together, then this happens, then this is the response, then that's the response.
[SPEAKER_02]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_02]: I'm cleared.
[SPEAKER_02]: But, again, you can't, as I said, you can't just magically stop doing that.
[SPEAKER_02]: There's going to be some tendency to explain.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's not going to be perfect, but if you keep looking beyond it, as in like, okay, I am still putting pieces together and trying this and trying that, but overall, when I'm touched by suffering, do I need to do anything?
[SPEAKER_02]: Is there any impulse, a compulsion, to explain it to myself?
[SPEAKER_02]: What happened here?
[SPEAKER_02]: Why?
[SPEAKER_02]: Why do I have to do that?
[SPEAKER_02]: Why can't I just understand things as they are, without needing to go through the self-explanatory loops?
[SPEAKER_02]: Why can't in the scene just be the scene?
[SPEAKER_02]: What I've seen is just to the extent that it's seen.
[SPEAKER_02]: I don't need to be saying what happened behind the scenes to feel comfortable with this.
[SPEAKER_02]: In perceived, there's just perceived.
[SPEAKER_02]: In the felt, there will be just the felt.
[SPEAKER_02]: Why can't I stay with that the most, the broadest, often most ambiguous, yet, as I said, real as such level?
[SPEAKER_02]: Why do I need... Why do I have to explain my feelings to myself?
[SPEAKER_02]: Why can't I just stop short?
[SPEAKER_02]: Can I recognize stopping short real as such?
[SPEAKER_02]: Or is the impulse to complete the sentence internally, of what has just occurred, taken for granted, and I always just act out of it.
[SPEAKER_02]: So it's like a deeply rooted psychological mental habit, need, that comes from that need to just deal with suffering.
[SPEAKER_02]: And that's why it's fundamentally just inseparable from avijjā.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, where would you then start to try to identify?
[SPEAKER_00]: Because I think for anybody who's taken on the precepts, trying to develop restraint and sīla to a certain extent, there is the very easy tendency of whenever you start to suffer, to say, oh, well, it must be because of failure in morality and this or that.
[SPEAKER_00]: It doesn't seem to me like that's always 100% wrong.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, it can be accurate.
[SPEAKER_00]: But when does that... Basically, how do you make sure that you're doing that correctly?
[SPEAKER_02]: Well, I think that's what I mean, like, stopping the mid-sentence.
[SPEAKER_02]: The first half of the sentence would be just the thoughts that the mind came up with, which often might be even factual.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's what I said, like, in the previous conversations, like, oh, I did that because he said this, and he was deserving it, and he was really unpleasant, and I needed to put him in his place.
[SPEAKER_02]: And that might be 100% true.
[SPEAKER_02]: Those facts.
[SPEAKER_02]: But the fact is, if you acted out of ill will, that's always on you, that part.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, this is the same, like, you start keeping the precepts, start trying to figure things out, but as things arise, as challenges present themselves,
[SPEAKER_02]: You kind of, say, recognize to some extent, like, okay, well, the problem here is maybe, you know, I slipped in the precepts, I acted out, so that's why there's... and it's like, you will, you will feel the line, so to speak.
[SPEAKER_02]: You will see where, where that recognition and that, say, like, thought process comes up to a certain extent, and when it becomes emotionally charged, that's the difference here.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, it's like, oh, it's because...
[SPEAKER_02]: But now there is this kind of vacuum left, of unfulfilled pressure.
[SPEAKER_02]: Well, let me repeat this again, the same information, to feed this, pretty much, this pressure that is there.
[SPEAKER_02]: And that's now passing the mid-sentence.
[SPEAKER_02]: Now you're adding out.
[SPEAKER_02]: So it feels... Again, I say mid-sentence because you start from the position of overdoing, making those mistakes, doing psychologizations.
[SPEAKER_02]: But in reality, the extent that it has arisen, it's sufficient enough.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's already a finished sentence.
[SPEAKER_02]: The fact that you feel ambiguous about it, does not make the mental sentence unfinished.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's your own view that paints it that way, and then you keep adding more.
[SPEAKER_02]: But again, the framework will never be satisfied.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, there's never gonna end the proliferation of adding more and needing more information.
[SPEAKER_02]: See, if you never see the problem of that mental habit of psychologizing, it's infinitely hungry.
[SPEAKER_02]: Like, there is no end to then you needing new things, new angles, new interpretations, new explanations, new techniques, new practices to keep feeding that furnace, basically.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because the things become stale if you just repeat the same psychological pattern.
[SPEAKER_02]: They don't offer the relief anymore.
[SPEAKER_02]: So you need to embellish, you need to change, you need to find a different...
[SPEAKER_02]: A different take on those things.
[SPEAKER_02]: And it's never-ending, because again, that's not where the root of the problem was.
[SPEAKER_01]: And so, in terms of... there's one sutta that says, one cannot come to the end of dukkha without understanding the Four Noble Truths.
[SPEAKER_01]: Such a thing is not possible.
[SPEAKER_01]: You have to understand the Four Noble Truths to bring an end to suffering.
[SPEAKER_01]: So...
[SPEAKER_01]: So, one can read there and say, well, I have to now understand
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, what is suffering?
[SPEAKER_01]: What is the cause of suffering?
[SPEAKER_02]: Okay, well, the Buddha says this in the Sutta and... Yeah, that's why, again, learning is indispensable.
[SPEAKER_02]: You need to have the right information, the right instruction.
[SPEAKER_02]: We spoke about it so many times.
[SPEAKER_02]: At the same time, like, if you are not transparent enough, as I said, you will
[SPEAKER_02]: Often, confuse the learning for making connections between mental information.
[SPEAKER_02]: As in, sorry, you will confuse understanding for mere learning.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, I know the suttas, I know the Pali, I know all the terms, how they connect, I can explain them.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's like, yeah, that's the informational level that is necessary.
[SPEAKER_02]: But does that informational level, or have you also learned about, through information, the necessity of self-transparency and precepts?
[SPEAKER_02]: That can then elevate your merely informational level to the actual practice.
[SPEAKER_02]: Why?
[SPEAKER_02]: Well, because if you're truly understanding those terms, you would not be affected by dukkha emotionally.
[SPEAKER_02]: You wouldn't need to do anything on account of the arisen dukkha, because you are not affected by it to begin with.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, if that criteria, if that reference point, that understanding leads to freedom from suffering here and now, at the most deepest existential level, you are free.
[SPEAKER_02]: If that criteria is not known, learned, maintained, discerned, you're not understanding anything.
[SPEAKER_02]: Your understanding is just understanding relative to information that you have.
[SPEAKER_02]: And often, again, as I said, even in my own practice, in my process of, like, learning and collecting, I remember, like, you know, reading this book or that book and the sutra translation and stuff, and often it was just like a, like, almost like a comparative study.
[SPEAKER_02]: And I didn't understand why it was wrong back then, to what extent it was wrong, but I remember I couldn't quite
[SPEAKER_02]: Makes sense.
[SPEAKER_02]: How would this free the liability to suffer here on the, as I said, the most personal level?
[SPEAKER_02]: There was just nothing there.
[SPEAKER_02]: It was just, oh, you just do this.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, it kind of almost became again like another, as I said, mechanical method of just, just, just, just fitting the puzzles of the information, the pieces of connecting, finding angles, writing about it, kind of fleshing it out and so on.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's like, but here and now,
[SPEAKER_02]: What is your motivation to do that?
[SPEAKER_02]: Have you included that in your informational Jenga puzzle?
[SPEAKER_02]: And it's like, no, that's like, that's kind of like assumed that those things will just happen by themselves, that, you know, purification of your own relationship with your own mind and your feelings and acting out on the body, speech and mind.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's like, oh, so then all the information in the world will not free you from suffering.
[SPEAKER_02]: Like, you can read the Pali study suttas all you want.
[SPEAKER_02]: It will take you in the direction of, as I said, informational knowledge that's now filled the place for understanding for you.
[SPEAKER_02]: Again, somebody's gonna think, ah, so I must stop reading.
[SPEAKER_02]: No.
[SPEAKER_02]: You should, by all means, keep reading study suttas, understand the terms, get to the bottom of, like, the key Pali terms, so that you have your own clear view as to what that means, and you can explain to somebody else.
[SPEAKER_02]: But at the same time, maintain the reference point as to, okay, I'm doing this and keeping an eye onto my overall ability to suffer and act out of lust, act out of aversion, because if these things are understood, this should be diminishing.
[SPEAKER_02]: If I'm truly thinking along the lines of the correct dhamma, after I finish the thinking, the desire will be far away.
[SPEAKER_02]: The possibility of ill will will be far away.
[SPEAKER_02]: Not that I'll be immediately anāgāmī.
[SPEAKER_02]: It can come back if I become careless, but it will be far away.
[SPEAKER_02]: It won't be like five minutes later.
[SPEAKER_02]: Craving is there.
[SPEAKER_02]: Sensual thoughts are there.
[SPEAKER_02]: I was irritated by this.
[SPEAKER_02]: No.
[SPEAKER_02]: They would be the actual samādhi as the result of right thinking along the lines of the right dhamma.
[SPEAKER_01]: You say it's because you're actually living what you're reading.
[SPEAKER_01]: You know, you're actually seeing what you're reading.
[SPEAKER_02]: Well, yeah, that's the point.
[SPEAKER_02]: Like, you are reading it.
[SPEAKER_02]: You need to transcend the level of, like, I'm reading it for the informational purposes.
[SPEAKER_02]: I'm reading it so to see those things here and now on the level of my own mind, on the level of my own experience.
[SPEAKER_02]: And I said that in all talks, like,
[SPEAKER_02]: I remember that, you know, I would be walking back and forth and, like, you know, contemplating and so on.
[SPEAKER_02]: And then it occurred to me, I was like, what is viññāṇa?
[SPEAKER_02]: Like, it's consciousness.
[SPEAKER_02]: We translate it as consciousness.
[SPEAKER_02]: In this language, it's translated like that.
[SPEAKER_02]: In that language, like, but what is it?
[SPEAKER_02]: Like, I know it's consciousness.
[SPEAKER_02]: Like, yeah, but what is consciousness?
[SPEAKER_02]: It's like... but instead of just... oh, let me find another definition now that I can say that's what consciousness is and, like, shift from one information... oh, viññāṇa.
[SPEAKER_02]: Oh, yeah, well, viññāṇa is consciousness.
[SPEAKER_02]: Oh, but what's consciousness?
[SPEAKER_02]: Well, consciousness is actually... and then, whatever, adopt some other view.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's like, well, but that's still not, like, telling me what consciousness is here and now.
[SPEAKER_02]: Those are just, like, passing information from one to the other to the other onto the next information.
[SPEAKER_02]: Like, so what is consciousness?
[SPEAKER_02]: When I say consciousness, consciousness,
[SPEAKER_02]: What am I referring to?
[SPEAKER_02]: Like, when I say left arm, I know I'm referring to this thing.
[SPEAKER_02]: But when I say consciousness, what am I referring to in this space and time of my experience as a whole?
[SPEAKER_02]: What am I referring to when I say consciousness?
[SPEAKER_02]: And then I thought, oh, well, that's a good question.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's like, hold on, let's take something simpler.
[SPEAKER_02]: When I say rūpa, what am I referring to?
[SPEAKER_02]: When I say vedanā, what am I referring to?
[SPEAKER_02]: Oh, it's feeling.
[SPEAKER_02]: What am I referring to?
[SPEAKER_02]: Where is that thing?
[SPEAKER_02]: Can I describe it in any other terms?
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's how you understand it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, exactly.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's how you get to see the actual phenomena that you are referring to.
[SPEAKER_01]: Without having...
[SPEAKER_02]: Without having to adopt another external standpoint.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Explanation.
[SPEAKER_02]: For as long as you're not seeing those phenomena as livingly designated here and now, so to speak, they are at the arm's length.
[SPEAKER_02]: They are from the external standpoint.
[SPEAKER_02]: They are theoretical.
[SPEAKER_02]: They are abstract.
[SPEAKER_02]: Even if you know in and out the etymology, the root, the language, what it refers to, you can compare it to six different takes on it.
[SPEAKER_02]: For you, it's still not pertaining to the right level and it's still not freeing you from suffering.
[SPEAKER_02]: And it never will, because no amount of information can bridge that gap.
[SPEAKER_02]: So...
[SPEAKER_02]: Learning is necessary, but learning will be a lot more efficient, a lot less likely to become proliferating in these abstractly theoretical ways that are confused for the, oh, this is the truth that I know now, although I'm not free from suffering, if it's paired with the actual mental training.
[SPEAKER_02]: Withdrawal from the unwholesome actions, taming of the mind.
[SPEAKER_02]: Then, you wouldn't need even half of the information to see the things
[SPEAKER_02]: That those very suttas talk about.
[SPEAKER_02]: Viññāṇa.
[SPEAKER_02]: Do you see viññāṇa?
[SPEAKER_02]: Do you see the aggregate of viññāṇa?
[SPEAKER_02]: Like, for yourself.
[SPEAKER_02]: Not, do you see another take, someone else's writing of what viññāṇa is.
[SPEAKER_02]: When I see viññāṇa, I think about someone else's words.
[SPEAKER_02]: Like, no, do I see that phenomenon without using any words?
[SPEAKER_02]: Do I just, in the same sense, like, I say my left arm?
[SPEAKER_02]: I don't need to keep saying to myself what my left arm is.
[SPEAKER_02]: I see it.
[SPEAKER_02]: Mentally, I recognize it, what it is.
[SPEAKER_01]: Even in dukkha, suffering?
[SPEAKER_02]: Anything.
[SPEAKER_02]: Well, that's the whole point.
[SPEAKER_02]: It occurred to me in regard to viññāṇa, I remember.
[SPEAKER_02]: But then, exactly, so what is dukkha, then?
[SPEAKER_02]: What is tantra, then?
[SPEAKER_02]: Being free from suffering?
[SPEAKER_02]: Well, what is that?
[SPEAKER_02]: What do I mean by that?
[SPEAKER_02]: Like, I have a vague notion of freedom, but what does that actually entail for me?
[SPEAKER_02]: What do I think it is?
[SPEAKER_02]: Am I clear on that?
[SPEAKER_02]: Or I'm just, like, just going along with this, like, half-baked, unclarified, mostly obscured ideas that came on account of even the right information, but then never, like, pushed further internally?
[SPEAKER_02]: It's not just like, can I explain tanhā, dukkha or consciousness in some words?
[SPEAKER_02]: Can I see it for myself without even explaining it?
[SPEAKER_02]: When I say tanhā, can I immediately see what that refers to?
[SPEAKER_02]: And it says, citta, can I see what that refers to?
[SPEAKER_02]: So the suttas become a very different ballgame then, if that becomes your standard of understanding.
[SPEAKER_02]: Everything that you've been taking for granted and reading, because it makes sense, it's written, and there is a context you follow, you understand it on some level.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's easy.
[SPEAKER_02]: But it's like, oh, but now...
[SPEAKER_02]: Obviously, this addresses the training in higher mind, the five types of thoughts, that everybody thinks they can do it.
[SPEAKER_02]: Just think the opposite and do this.
[SPEAKER_02]: But the whole thing applies to the higher mind training.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's like, okay, so the higher citta.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, am I even seeing the lower citta?
[SPEAKER_02]: Like, when it says citta, do I see that phenomenon of citta here and now?
[SPEAKER_02]: I just have a vague idea about it that pleases me and makes sense.
[SPEAKER_02]: And then I build on top of that.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's like, oh, so then I got to see the mind and then this whole...
[SPEAKER_02]: Everything else that follows in the sutta will probably read very differently then, if I see the citta.
[SPEAKER_02]: You'll probably have a lot more acute, direct, efficient instruction than just, oh, think the opposite and hope for the best type of thing.
[SPEAKER_02]: Wish love to everybody and so on.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's like, no, it's like directly seeing the citta, and then when he has these thoughts, you also provide this context.
[SPEAKER_02]: When he has those thoughts, well, you provide this context.
[SPEAKER_02]: On that level.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's like, oh, it's getting too tight?
[SPEAKER_02]: I'm loosening it.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's getting too loose?
[SPEAKER_02]: I'm tightening it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Tune is becoming perfect.
[SPEAKER_01]: And you're understanding the mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: Of course.
[SPEAKER_02]: And the mind is calming down as a result of it.
[SPEAKER_02]: And as it says, you know, the calm mind, the joy arises, the joy, the clear seeing, the understanding, the liberation.
[SPEAKER_02]: The problem is, obviously, the informational knowledge can be very convincing.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, then, you end up... Of course, yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, you end up very convinced and safe in your explanatory system of ideas, of satisfying ideas that provide safety.
[SPEAKER_02]: And you know the answer to everything.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because you read all the suttas.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, that's this, and this, and this, and this.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, this internal level of your intention in regard to that, and everything else we talk about, will also become part of something that you, through psychologization, explain back, and have answers for.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's like, so why would I... why would I need to...
[SPEAKER_01]: I already understood it, I have an answer for it.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, you need to... that person, any person, needs to be transparent enough to recognize, yeah, but... and ask themselves, but am I free from suffering?
[SPEAKER_02]: Without having to explain anything.
[SPEAKER_02]: Without having to do anything, is the suffering still touching me or not?
[SPEAKER_02]: Because if that's absent, no amount of information can make you open your eyes.
[SPEAKER_02]: It will just distract you further, so to speak.
[SPEAKER_02]: And that's what... That's what Yanavera...
[SPEAKER_02]: I think Yanavera said in one of the letters, when apparently some logician was given suttas to read, and he said, well, this weird, like, this is all just mere tautology.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because he could not conceive that this is to be done.
[SPEAKER_02]: He was approaching everything through information of A, B, C. So, if it's this, then it's this, then it's that.
[SPEAKER_02]: I read it.
[SPEAKER_02]: Sutta's finished.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, he thought suttas are just self-explanatory statements.
[SPEAKER_02]: Which, if you don't have the idea of training, they are.
[SPEAKER_02]: Oh, you'll be free from ignorance.
[SPEAKER_02]: You'll be free from avijja when you make the effort and free yourself from avijja.
[SPEAKER_01]: Aha, okay, well, thank you.
[SPEAKER_02]: I know that now.
[SPEAKER_02]: Therefore, my work is complete.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's like, no.
[SPEAKER_02]: Have you trained?
[SPEAKER_02]: Have you done the things in between, so to say?
[SPEAKER_02]: But if even the things in between, the training, is taken as self-explanatory statements, then you're never going to take on anything.
[SPEAKER_02]: And then even if you take on the practices of keeping the precepts and training and stuff, but still not using that internal living criteria of can I be touched by suffering, you know, whether I have a perfect explanation and technique to manage it or not,
[SPEAKER_02]: You will fall again into one view or the other that would be semi-abstract, semi-psychology, kind of psychologizing these layers of avoiding responsibility, covering it up, building up a system that provides safety through explanation.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because familiarity of explanation, that gets confused for understanding.
[SPEAKER_02]: Oh, it makes sense.
[SPEAKER_02]: I, pleases me.
[SPEAKER_02]: Not like, makes sense, I can't be touched by suffering.
[SPEAKER_02]: Make sense equals pleases me.
[SPEAKER_02]: Therefore, or what pleases me equals makes sense.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, it's fine to, like, as I said, you can't just switch it off.
[SPEAKER_02]: The tendency of thinking like that.
[SPEAKER_02]: But, you certainly can make the effort and not lose the sight of the bigger picture, which is, sure, I'm contemplating, I'm collecting information, I'm connecting dots in space and time of how things work.
[SPEAKER_02]: But,
[SPEAKER_02]: Also, to bring it back home on the level of in the scene, the scene is seen.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's it.
[SPEAKER_02]: There is no other loops of having to add extra tidbits of knowledge to make sense, because it's already understood on the level it has arisen.
[SPEAKER_02]: And that can only be done if that criteria and the widest reference point is understanding leads to freedom from suffering, freedom from a liability to suffer.
[SPEAKER_02]: Understanding anything, understanding rūpa, understanding the term viññāṇa, understanding the term dukkha, understanding the term vedanā, pick a term, any aggregate, noble truth, whatever, understand it, that means you are unable to suffer even if you want to.
[SPEAKER_02]: So that criteria must remain clarified and acknowledged throughout.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because that's what will keep you in check when you go through your ramblings and roaming mentally and, you know, habits.
[SPEAKER_02]: This will still keep you relatively aligned.
[SPEAKER_02]: But if you dismiss that, then...